I'm a lexicographer.
أنا مؤلفة قواميس.
I make dictionaries.
أؤلف قواميس.
And my job as a lexicographer
ووظيفتي كمؤلفة قواميس
is to try to put all the words possible into the dictionary.
هي محاولة إدراج القدر الممكن من الكلمات بداخل القاموس.
My job is not to decide what a word is; that is your job.
وظيفتي ليست معنية بتحديد ماهية الكلمة، تلك هي وظيفتكم.
Everybody who speaks English decides together
كل الأشخاص الذين يتحدثون الإنجليزية، هم من يحددون معًا
what's a word and what's not a word.
ما الكلمة وما التي ليست بكلمة.
Every language is just a group of people who agree to understand each other.
كل لغة ليست إلا مجموعة من الأفراد اتفقوا على أن يفهم كل منهم الآخر.
Now, sometimes when people are trying to decide whether a word is good or bad,
في بعض الأحيان، عندما يحدد الناس كلمةً ما إذا كانت جيدة أو سيئة،
they don't really have a good reason.
فإنهم في الحقيقة لا يملكون سبب مقنع.
So they say something like, "Because grammar!"
لهذا، فإنهم يرددون غالبًا، "بسبب القواعد اللغوية"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I don't actually really care about grammar too much -- don't tell anybody.
في الحقيقة أنا لا أكترث جدًا بالقواعد - لا تخبروا أحدًا.
But the word "grammar," actually, there are two kinds of grammar.
بالنسبة لكلمة "القواعد" يوجد هناك نوعين من القواعد.
There's the kind of grammar that lives inside your brain,
يوجد نوع من القواعد يسكن بداخل عقلك،
and if you're a native speaker of a language
فإذا كنت ابن لغة معينة
or a good speaker of a language,
أو متحدث جيد لهذه اللغة،
it's the unconscious rules that you follow when you speak that language.
فإنك تتبع هذه القواعد بشكل تلقائي عندما تتحدث بتلك اللغة.
And this is what you learn when you learn a language as a child.
هذا ما تتعلمه عندما تتعلم اللغة كطفل.
And here's an example:
وهنا مثال:
This is a wug, right?
هذا فرخ، صحيح؟
It's a wug.
إنه فرخ.
Now there is another one.
هنا يوجد فرخ آخر.
There are two of these.
هنا يوجد اثنان منهما.
There are two ...
هنا يوجد اثنان ...
Audience: Wugs.
الحضور: من الفراخ
Erin McKean: Exactly! You know how to make the plural of wug.
ايرين ماكين : بالضبط، فأنتم تعرفون كيف تصنعون جمعًا للفراخ لغويًا.
That rule lives in your brain.
تلك القاعدة تسكن بداخل عقلك.
You never had to be taught this rule, you just understand it.
فمن المستحيل أنك قد تعلمتها، فقط أنت تفهمها.
This is an experiment that was invented by a professor at [Boston University]
هذه تجربة ابُتكرت بواسطة دكتور بجامعة بوسطن
named Jean Berko Gleason back in 1958.
يُدعى جان بيركو جيلسون في ١٩٥٨م.
So we've been talking about this for a long time.
تحدثنا عن هذا طويلًا.
Now, these kinds of natural rules that exist in your brain,
أما الآن، هذه الأنواع من القواعد الطبيعية التي توجد بعقلك.
they're not like traffic laws, they're more like laws of nature.
إنها ليست كأنظمة المرور، إنها أكثر شبهً بقوانين الطبيعة.
And nobody has to remind you to obey a law of nature, right?
فليس من الحاجة أن يُذكرك شخص بإتباع قوانين الطبيعة، صحيح؟
When you leave the house in the morning, your mom doesn't say,
عندما تغادر المنزل في الصباح، لا تقول لك أمك:
"Hey, honey, I think it's going to be cold, take a hoodie,
"مهلاً، حبيبي، أعتقد أن اليوم سيكون باردًا،خذ سترة صوفية
don't forget to obey the law of gravity."
لا تنسى أن تطيع قانون الجاذبية.
Nobody says this.
لا شخص يقول مثل هذا.
Now, there are other rules that are more about manners than they are about nature.
أما الآن، توجد قواعد أخرى أكثر قربًا للأساليب من قربها للطبيعة
So you can think of a word as like a hat.
بإمكانك أن تفكر في كلمة، مثل "قُبعة"
Once you know how hats work,
حالما تعرف كيف تُرتدى القبعة،
nobody has to tell you, "Don't wear hats on your feet."
لست بحاجة لشخص يقول لك: "لا تلبسها على قدمك".
What they have to tell you is, "Can you wear hats inside?
ما بإمكان الناس أن يفعلوه إخبارك "هل تستطيع أن ترتديها داخل المنزل؟"
Who gets to wear a hat?
من الذي يرتدي قبعة؟
What are the kinds of hats you get to wear?"
أي نوع من القبعات ترتدي؟
Those are more of the second kind of grammar,
هذا هو النوع الثاني من قواعد اللغة.
which linguists often call usage, as opposed to grammar.
التي يطلق عليها اللغويون غالبًا "معارضة للقواعد".
Now, sometimes people use this kind of rules-based grammar
بعض الأحيان، يستخدم الناس هذا النوع من القواعد المعتمد على النحو
to discourage people from making up words.
لتثبيط الناس عن ابتكار كلمات.
And I think that is, well, stupid.
وإني لأظن أن هذا غباء.
So, for example, people are always telling you,
سأقدم لكم مثال : "الناس عادةً يقولون لك
"Be creative, make new music, do art, invent things, science and technology."
إبدع، ابتكر موسيقى جديدة، قم بعمل فني، اخترع أشياءً في العلوم والتكنولوجيا".
But when it comes to words, they're like,
لكن ما إن تأتي إلى تلك الكلمات، تجد وكأنها
"Don't! No. Creativity stops right here, whippersnappers. Give it a rest."
تقول لا، لا تفعل، "الإبداع حينها يتوقف، ونقدم له قسطًا من الراحة".
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But that makes no sense to me.
هذا غير منطقي بالنسبة لي.
Words are great. We should have more of them.
الكلمات عظيمة، ينبغي أن يكون لدينا الكثير منها.
I want you to make as many new words as possible.
أريد منك أن تبتكر قدر المستطاع كلماتٍ جديدة.
And I'm going to tell you six ways that you can use to make new words in English.
سأقول لكم ست طرق بإمكانك من خلالها ابتكار كلمات جديدة في اللغة الإنجليزية.
The first way is the simplest way.
أول طريقة أبسط طريقة.
Basically, steal them from other languages.
ببساطة، اسرقوا الكلمات من لغاتٍ أخرى.
["Go rob other people"] (Laughter)
هيا لنسرق أُناس أخرين (ضحك)
Linguists call this borrowing,
اللغويون يسمون هذه مجرد استعارة.
but we never give the words back , so I'm just going to be honest
لكننا لم نُعيد تلك الكلمات أبدًا، فقط لأكون صادقة.
and call it stealing.
فلنُسمها سرقة.
We usually take words for things that we like, like delicious food.
عادةً نسرق الكلمات للأشياء التي تعجبنا، مثلًا الطعام لذيذ.
We took "kumquat" from Chinese, we took "caramel" from French.
فأخذنا "كمقوات" من اللغة الصينية، وأخذنا "كراميل" من الفرنسية.
We also take words for cool things like "ninja," right?
بالإضافة نسرق الكلمات للأشياء الرائعة مثل نينجا، صحيح؟
We took that from Japanese,
أخذناها من اللغة اليابانية.
which is kind of a cool trick because ninjas are hard to steal from.
والتي هي نوعًا من الخدع الرائعة لأن النينجا من الصعب سرقتها
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So another way that you can make words in English
الطريقة الأخرى التي تمكنك من ابتكار كلمات للغة الإنجليزية
is by squishing two other English words together.
هي الجمع بين كلمتان انجليزيتان معًا
This is called compounding.
تسمى بعملية الدمج.
Words in English are like Lego:
الكلمات الإنجليزية تشبه الليجو:
If you use enough force, you can put any two of them together.
إذا استخدمت الطريقة الملائمة، بإمكانك أن تجمع كل كلمتين معًا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
We do this all the time in English:
نقوم بهذه الطريقة في اللغة الإنجليزية:
Words like "heartbroken," "bookworm," "sandcastle" all are compounds.
مثل كلمة "Heartbroken" و "Bookworm" و "Sandcastle" كلها كلمات مدموجة.
So go ahead and make words like "duckface," just don't make duckface.
حسنًا، انطلق لتبتكر كلمات مثل "Duckface" لكن لا تفعل تلك الحركة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Another way that you can make words in English is kind of like compounding,
الطريقة الأخرى لصناعة الكلمات في اللغة الإنجليزية هي نوع من الدمج.
but instead you use so much force when you squish the words together
لكن بدلًا من أن تجمع بين كلمتين, تقوم بالتوليف بين كلمتين
that some parts fall off.
أي أن بعض أجزاء الكلمة ستُسقط.
So these are blend words,
وستصبح كلمات مؤلفة،
like "brunch" is a blend of "breakfast" and "lunch."
مثلا كلمة "Brunch" هي كلمة مؤلفة من كلمتي "Breakfast" و "Lunch"
"Motel" is a blend of "motor" and "hotel."
"Motel" مؤلفة من "Motor" و "Hotel."
Who here knew that "motel" was a blend word?
هل هنا من يعرف أن "Motel" كانت كلمة مؤلفة؟
Yeah, that word is so old in English
نعم، كلمة إنجليزية قديمة جدًا
that lots of people don't know that there are parts missing.
وأن الكثير من الناس لا يعرفون أنه يوجد أحرف مفقودة منها.
"Edutainment" is a blend of "education" and "entertainment."
"Edutainment" كلمة مؤلفة من "Education" و "Entertainment"
And of course, "electrocute" is a blend of "electric" and "execute."
و بالطبع "Electrocute" كلمة مؤلفة من "Electric" و "Execute"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
You can also make words by changing how they operate.
بالإضافة يمكنك أن تبتكر كلمات عن طريق تغيير الكيفية التي وظفت لها.
This is called functional shift.
تسمى بطريقة التحول الوظيفي.
You take a word that acts as one part of speech,
خذ كلمة لها وظيفة واحدة في تركيبة الجملة،
and you change it into another part of speech.
وقم بتغيير وظيفتها لوظيفة أخرى في تركيبة الجملة.
Okay, who here knew that "friend" hasn't always been a verb?
حسنًا، هل هنا من يعرف أن كلمة "Friend" لم تكن دائمًا فعل ؟
"Friend" used to be noun and then we verbed it.
كلمة" Friend" اعتدنا على أن تكون اسم، ثم جعلناها فعل.
Almost any word in English can be verbed.
تقريبًا أي كلمة في اللغة الإنجليزية من الممكن أن تكون فعل.
You can also take adjectives and make them into nouns.
أيضا بإمكانك أن تأخذ الصفات وتجعل منها أسماءً.
"Commercial" used to be an adjective and now it's a noun.
"Commercial" اعتدنا أن تكون صفة والآن هي اسم.
And of course, you can "green" things.
بالطبع، يمكنك "تخضير" الأشياء.
Another way to make words in English is back-formation.
الطريقة الأخرى لصنع الكلمات هي "صياغة النهايات".
You can take a word and you can kind of squish it down a little bit.
بمقدورك أن تأخذ كلمة ومن ثم تحذف نهايتها.
So for example, in English we had the word "editor" before we had the word "edit."
هنا مثال: في اللغة الإنجليزية أوجدنا كلمة "Editor" قبل كلمة "Edit".
"Edit" was formed from "editor."
فكلمة "Edit" تشكلت من كلمة "Editor".
Sometimes these back-formations sound a little silly:
أحيانًا، ما تكون طريقة "صياغة النهايات" نوعًا ما سخيفة:
Bulldozers bulldoze, butlers butle and burglers burgle.
Bulldozers bulldoze, butlers butler and burglars burgle.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Another way to make words in English
طريقة أخرى لصنع الكلمات الإنجليزية.
is to take the first letters of something and squish them together.
هي أخذ الحروف الأولى من عدة كلمات ومن ثم جمعها معًا.
So National Aeronautics and Space Administration becomes NASA.
مثلاُ National Aeronautics and Space Administration تُصبح NASA.
And of course you can do this with anything, OMG!
وبالطبع يمكن فعل ذات الطريقة مع أي شيء، OMG!
So it doesn't matter how silly the words are.
لايهم كيف ستبدو سخافة تلك الكلمات.
They can be really good words of English.
فمن الممكن أن تكون كلمات انجليزية مفيدة.
"Absquatulate" is a perfectly good word of English.
"Absquatulate" كلمة انجليزية مفيدة جدًا.
"Mugwump" is a perfectly
"Mugwump" كلمة انجليزية مفيدة جدًا.
So the words don't have have to sound normal, they can sound really silly.
كون تلك الكلمات صوتها غير طبيعي، فمن الممكن أن تكون سخيفة.
Why should you make words?
لماذا ينبغي عليك أن تبتكر كلمات؟
You should make words because every word
ينبغي أن تبتكر كلمات لأن كل كلمة
is a chance to express your idea and get your meaning across.
بمثابة فرصة من خلالها تستطيع أن تعبر عن فكرتك ومعناها
And new words grab people's attention.
الكلمات الجديدة تجذب إهتمام الناس،
They get people to focus on what you're saying
وتدفع الناس للتركيز على ما تود أن تقوله
and that gives you a better chance to get your meaning across.
وتمنحك أنت فرصة أكبر لإيصال المعنى الذي تريده.
A lot of people on this stage today have said,
الكثير منكم على هذا المسرح اليوم قد حدث نفسه،
"In the future, you can do this,
"في المستقبل، نستطيع فعل ذلك،
you can help with this, you can help us explore, you can help us invent."
بمقدورنا أن نساعد هذا، أن نكتشف، أن نخترع"
You can make a new word right now.
يمكنك أن تبتكر كلمات جديدة الآن.
English has no age limit.
الإنجليزية ليس لها عمر محدد.
Go ahead, start making words today,
انطلق، وابدأ بإبتكار كلمات من اليوم.
send them to me, and I will put them in my online dictionary, Wordnik.
أرسلهن إلي، ومن ثم سأقوم بإضافتهن إلى قاموسي الإلكتروني "Wordnik"
Thank you so much.
شكرًا جزيلًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)